<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Petitjon [sic] from the towne and county of Leicester unto the Kings most excellent Majesty. Also an other petition from the grand inquest of the same county unto his Majesty for the remouing of the magazine. : With his Majesties answer therewith. : Likewise certain propositions to his Majesty by Captain Grey and the Earl of Stamfords souldiers touching the magazin. : Also a declaration from the knights, esquires, gentlemen, grand iury-men, and free-holders, in the county of Leicester.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90570</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1756A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R181708</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45789381</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45789381</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172691</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90570)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172691)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2645:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Petitjon [sic] from the towne and county of Leicester unto the Kings most excellent Majesty. Also an other petition from the grand inquest of the same county unto his Majesty for the remouing of the magazine. : With his Majesties answer therewith. : Likewise certain propositions to his Majesty by Captain Grey and the Earl of Stamfords souldiers touching the magazin. : Also a declaration from the knights, esquires, gentlemen, grand iury-men, and free-holders, in the county of Leicester.</title>
                  <author>Grey, Captain.</author>
                  <author>Stamford, Henry Grey, Earl of, 1599?-1673.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[1], 6, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.N. for William Gay ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642. July 30.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Christ Church (University of Oxford). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
               <term>Leicestershire (England) --  History --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172691:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 52 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:172691:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 52 -->
            <p>A PETITION From the Towne and County of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> unto the Kings moſt excellent Majeſty.</p>
            <p>Alſo an other Petition from the Grand Inqueſt of the ſame County unto his Majeſty for the remouing of the Magazine</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With his</hi> Majeſties <hi>Anſwer thereunto.</hi> Likewiſe certain Propoſitions to his <hi>Majeſty</hi> by Captain <hi>Grey</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Stamfords</hi> Souldiers touching the Magazin.</p>
            <p>Alſo a Declaration from the Knights, Eſ-quires, Gentlemen, Grand Iury-men, and Free-holders, in the County of <hi>Leiceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ordered to be printed by ſpeciall command.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>A.N.</hi> for <hi>William Gay,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Hoſier</hi> Lane at the ſigne of the Axe, 1642. July 30.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:172691:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 53 -->
            <head>
               <hi>To the Kings moſt excellent Majeſtie.</hi> The humble petition of the Inhabitants of the Town and County of <hi>Leiceſter.</hi> JULY 22.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Cknowledging your Majeſties Princely proteſtations for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Proteſtant Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Lawes of the Land, (which your Highneſſe makes the juſteſt meaſure and rule of your royall prerogative, the liberty and obedience of your ſubjects as alſo for the peace of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, diſavowing not only intentions of war, as opening an iſſue to drown your Majeſty &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, but alſo taking care that no poſture ſhould affright the ſubjects.</p>
            <p>Yet we cannot but in all humility expreſſe our deep ſorrows for your Majeſties long eſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from, and oppoſition to your higheſt and ſafeſt Councell of Parliament; on the ſucceſſe whereof the ſafety, honour, and glory of your
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:172691:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 53 -->Majeſty and happineſſe of your ſubjects doth depend.</p>
            <p>Well, we can never expect while we ſee De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents protected againſt the juſtice of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, promoted to Honour and Offices of high truſt and power, ſuch as M. <hi>Henry Haſtings,</hi> who after he had appeared in an hoſtile manner to the great terrour of your Majeſties peaceable ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and was reſcued from the Miniſter of Parliament, did notwithſtanding (to the greater affrightment of all &amp; miſcarrying of divers wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) came with a troope of Horſe and Foot at midnight to <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> demanding the Magazine, and proclayming the Earl of <hi>Stamford</hi> and divers others by name with all their adherents traitors, and after all this is protected (as wee conceive) and made high Sheriff, and an approved Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man caſt out for no other cauſe appearing to us then the diſcharging of his duty to your Majeſty and the parliament.</p>
            <p>Wee are deeply affected with theſe proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, as preſaging the ruine of all at once.</p>
            <p>Therefore wee humbly pray that your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Commiſſion of Array declared to be ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly againſt Law (which your Majeſty makes the rule of our allegeance and obedience) may be
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:172691:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 54 -->recalled, That juſtice may impartially proceed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Delinquents, without which a parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment cannot ſubſiſt, That you would caſhiere all ſuch deſperat perſons as would ingage the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in a bloudy civill War, and abandon all the Counſellours of Diviſion, That the honour and innocency of our worthy Knight, and the other five Members impeacht may be vindicated, That you would joyn your ſelf to your parliament, as the only way to ſave our ſelves and bleeding <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and that our M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gazine and <hi>Militia,</hi> may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in the hands of the honorable Earl of <hi>Stam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> who is inſtruſted by the parliament. Wee ſtand reſolved ever to maintain the true reformed proteſtant Religion, your Majeſties perſon and authority<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Laws and free courſe of Iuſtice, together with the high and honourable Court of parliament, as the Bottom wherein all is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barqued. Wee are Enemies to all that divide be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt your Majeſty and your parliament, or that have or ſhall affront or caſt baſe aſperſions on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t faithfull Aſſembly, and according to our juſt and free proteſtation, wee'l venture our eſtates and lives herein, and ſhall ever pray, &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:172691:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 54 -->
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <div type="body_of_petition">
               <head>To the Kings moſt excellent Majeſtie. The humble Petition of the great Inqueſt for the County of <hi>Leicester.</hi> JVLY 23.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee doe in all humbleneſſe acknowledge that during your Majeſties Reigne hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thertowe have enjoyd that which is the greateſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that can befal a Natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, a ſtable and uninterrupted peace, your Declaration expreſſes your Prince<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly deſires of your ſubjects peace and welfare, being therfore the preſages of bloud and ruine do impend and hang over our heads, wee are forced to ſeeke a preſervative by our addreſſes unto your Highneſſe, if it may ſtand therefore with your Princely wiſdome as wee judge it
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:172691:4"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 55 -->ſtands with the peace and ſafety of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, our humble deſire is that there may be a ſafe diſtribution of this Magazine to the ſeverall Hundreds in this County to be diſperſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in according to due proportions, and this to be done immediatly from the Magazine, That ſince it ſtands with the peace and ſafety of this County it may never be re-aſſumed but by a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall power, that the Keepers thereof may have their liberty and protection from dangers, for diſcharching their truſt. Thus ſhall you diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve theſe clouds of calamities that threaten us and elevate us to higher hopes of peace.</p>
               <closer>And we ſhall ever pray, &amp;c.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="propositions">
               <head>Propoſitions to his Majeſty from Captain <hi>Grey,</hi> and the reſt of the ſouldiers intruſted from the Earle of <hi>Stamford,</hi> touching the Magazine.</head>
               <p n="1">I That there may be a ſafe diſtribution of this Magazine to the ſeverall Hundreds in the County to be diſperſed therein ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to due proportion, and this to be done immediatly from the Magazine.</p>
               <p n="2">II That it may never be re-aſſumed againe but by a Legall power.</p>
               <p n="3">III That the Keepers of it may have their liberty and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection from dangers for diſcharging their Truſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:172691:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 55 -->
               <head>Given at the Court at <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> 
                  <date>IULY 24, 1642.</date>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Is Majeſty hath graciouſly conſidered this Petition, and commanded mee to returne this Anſwer, that as the Petitioners have enjoyed hitherto the bleſſing of peace un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Majeſties Government, ſo he hath never expreſſed a greater love of it, and a care to preſerve it, then by his late bearing ſo many indignities to avoid all diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of it, the which hee hopes will have that effect with his good ſubjects, that they will hence-for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward have as great a regard to his honour, as hee to their peace, of which if all other were equally tender, no preſage of bloud, &amp; ruine would hang over their heads. For your Magazine his Majeſty hath never looked upon this under any other conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration then to preſerve it for the County whoſe it is. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore upon complaint heretofore made to him, that ſome perſons had preſumed in warlike manner to leavy it without any lawfull authority, his Majeſty out of his good affection to this Countie gave direction to prevent future miſchief, that the ſame ſhould be reſtored to the diſpoſition of thoſe to whom it belongs, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fore well approves, that it be diſpoſed in ſuch manner and ſuch place as ſhall ſeeme beſt and fitteſt to the County, in which his Majeſty will not intermeddle. For the freeing and protecting the Keepers of the Magazin or their Seconds, his Majeſty knows not the meaning of the Petitioners, if they have had a lawfull truſt committed, and done nothing in diſcharge and execution thereof but what is warrantable, they need no other protection but that of the Law, but if in the violent and forcible removing the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazine, and in the circumſtances of keeping they have done any done any thing unjuſtifiable, his Majeſty believes no truſt boldly undertaken can excuſe them, and therefore expects that this be immediatly delivered by the Keepers to the diſpoſall of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty without condition.</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:172691:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 56 -->
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:172691:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 56 -->
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:172691:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 57 -->
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="declaration">
                           <opener>
                              <signed>CHARLES <hi>Rex.</hi>
                              </signed>
                           </opener>
                           <p>OUr will and pleaſure is, That all our Officers and loving ſubjects doe ſuffer the Bearers hereof to paſſe quietly to their own houſes.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <dateline>Given at our Court at <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> 
                                 <date>the 24 of <hi>Iuly,</hi> 1642.</date>
                              </dateline>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>WHereas the Grand Jury at the Generall Aſſizes held in the County of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> did prefer a Petition unto his Majeſty for the diſtribution of the Countries Magazin to be divided into every hundred, and therein diſperſed into every Town, according to the charge leavied upon them for the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereof.</p>
               <p>And whereas it was alſo further in the ſaid Petition deſired that the ſaid Magazine might not be re-aſſumed again. Therefore the Baronets, Knights, Eſquires, Gentlemen, Grand Jury-men and Free-holders, &amp;c. doe hereby declare. That whoſoever ſhall go about to re-aſſume or gather into one body again the ſaid Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zine, or any part thereof by any Authority whatſoever, ſhall be adjudged, eſteemed, reputed and taken to be an Enemy to, and a diſturber of the publick peace of this County. And becauſe no man may plead ignorance in this behalfe, It is agreed by all ſorts, ranks, and degrees of perſons above-named, That this Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be now openly read and publiſhed, with an audible voice, in the face of the County, at this Generall Aſſizes held for the County aforeſaid. Dated <date>the 25 of <hi>Iuly</hi> 1642.</date>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="declaration">
                           <head>The Copy of that the Grand Iury gave the Commanders of the Magazine.</head>
                           <p>VVE the Gentlemen of the Grand Jury for the County of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> have received the Magazine thereof from the Eaſt gate in the Newwork, and do under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take ſo neer as we may, that it ſhall be diſtributed to the ſeverall Hundreds, and therein diſperſed to every Towne, ſo neere as wee can equally. And that it ſhall be never re-aſſumed to our powers. In witneſſe whereof we have ſubſcribed our names <date>the 25 day of <hi>Iuly, Anno Domini</hi> 1642.</date> Atteſted by all the Grand Jury.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:172691:6"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 57 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
